A Guide to the Shepard Forman papers FA1451
Rockefeller Archive Center
Shepard Forman papers
1956-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
Forman, Shepard (1938)
New York University. Center on International Cooperation
Ford Foundation
FA1451
4.16 Cubic Feet 10 boxes (4 legal document containers, 6 letter document containers)
Biographical / Historical
Shepard Forman held multiple positions in the Ford Foundation related to international issues and founded the Center on International Cooperation at New York University. Forman received his Ph.D. in Anthropology from Columbia in 1966 with previous training in history, Brazilian studies, and Spanish language and literature. He completed post-doctoral work in development economics at the Institute for Development Studies at Sussex, England and field research in Northeast Brazil and Timor-Leste.
Between 1966 and 1969, he held professorships in anthropology at Indiana University, the University of Chicago, and the University of Michigan. In 1977, Forman took a leave of absence from the University of Michigan to work as a program officer for the Ford Foundation in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. In this position, he was involved in community economic and rural development while also coordinating a grantmaking program in economics and the social sciences to universities and research institutes.
In 1981, Forman became Program Officer-in-Charge of the Human Rights and Governance Program and served in that position until 1986. In 1987, the title of Program Officer-in-Charge was changed to Director. Forman served in that title until 1990. He was involved in public policy initiatives and assisted civil rights and international human rights organizations. Forman became Director of International Affairs programs at the Ford Foundation in 1991. As Director, he created a grantmaking program of research, policy analysis and public education on post-Cold War international relations. He held primary responsibility for Foundation programs in Russia and Eastern Europe and supervised 20 program and support staff in the fields of peacekeeping and disarmament, international law, international economics and development, and U.S. foreign policy. Forman left the Foundation in 1996 to found and direct the Center on International Cooperation (CIC) at New York University. The CIC's primary mission is to strengthen cooperative approaches among national governments, international organizations, and the wider policy community to advance peace, justice, and inclusion. Forman retired from the CIC in 2008. Forman served as president of the Life After Ford Foundation (LAFF) Society from 2008 until 2019.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated and transferred to the RAC in 2016 by Shepard Forman and was ingested in 2017 by the RAC as Accession 2017:010.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
1. Photographs, 1956-1993
2. Personal and Professional Papers, 1977-2016
3. Monthly Calendars, 1980-1995
4. Notepads - International Travel and Trip Notes, 1982-1986
Related Materials
Related collections include:
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office of the Program Director, Office Files of Shepard Forman (FA625)
Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean Program, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Field Office, Office Files of Shepard Forman (FA630)
Ford Foundation records, Human Rights and Governance Program, Program Director, Office Files of Shepard Forman (FA717)
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Shepard Forman (FA741)
Scope and Contents
The collection contains photographs, correspondence, monthly calendars, and notebooks filled with trip reports and travel notes related to Shepard Forman's career at the Ford Foundation and transition to Director of the Center on International Cooperation at New York University.
International relations; Human rights; Public policy
- Photographs, 1956-1993; 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Untitled Negatives - Brazil (?), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agricultural Development - Amazon Environmental Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trustees Trip - Bali, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amazon Trip - Prints and Negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Shepard Forman/David Arnold in India, circa 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agricultural Development Meeting - Amazon, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bali, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Souvenir from Machado Restaurante Tipico, Portugal (Paper Photo Frame and Photos), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amazon Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Trustees Meeting - Thailand, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dave Arnold; Terry Calder, Consultant; Shep Forman, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Trustees - Jakarta, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents
    1. David Arnold, Lynn Walker, Shepard Forman
    2. Peter Geithner, David Arnold, Shepard Forman
    3. David Arnold, June Zeitler, and Shep Forman
    4. Human Rights and Social Justice Staff
    5. Temple with Ford staff
  - Shep Forman, David Arnold - India (2 folders), undated (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Ford Foundation Group Photo, 1993 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Group Photo - India, 1988 April (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Personal and Professional Papers, 1977-2016; 2; 1.23 Cubic Feet 1 legal document box and 2 letter document boxes
  - Five Year Review Notes - Persistent Poverty, International Affairs, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Shep Forman Handwritten Notes - Advisory Group UN Financing, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Shepard Forman - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Meetings - Notes, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Shepard Forman Partial Grants List - Human Rights and Governance and Responsible Program Officer (RPO)/Co-Responsible Program Officer, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Amazon Strategy Meeting Documents - Itineraries and Agendas, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Invitation to Foundation-wide International Affairs Program Conference in Cairo and Trip to Israel - Memos, Schedules, and Handwritten Notes, 1989 October (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Trip Reports - South Africa and Zimbabwe, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Human Rights Retreat, 1986 April 30-May 2 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Transition to Ford Foundation, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Dorothy Nepper Marshall Symposium, Bryn Mawr College, 1986 November (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Includes remarks: Civil-Military Relations in Latin America - November 8, 1986
  - Brasil '79 - Brasil Social Science Fellowship Committee - Photographs, 1980 October (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Photos:
    1 - James Gardner, Juarez Brandao Lopes, Boris Fausto, Ruth Cardoso, Claus W. ---, Prescilla Kritz, Senior Secretary Ford Foundation, Shepard Forman, Jose Murito de Carvalho
    2 - Circa 1979 - Ford Foundation social science research fellowship committee, from L-R, Boris Fausto, Professor of History, University of Sao Paulo; James Gardner, Ford Foundation rep, Rio de Janeiro; Ruth Cardozo, anthropologish (University of Sao Paulo); Claus W. --, linguist; Juarez Bradao Lopes, University of Sao Paulo; Jose Munito, Political Scientist, Unio Institute of Poli Sci, then at Candido Mendez University; Fabio; Shepard Forman, Project Specialist, Social Sciences and Rural Development
    3 - roundtable discussion
  - Brasil '79 - Brasil Social Science Fellowship Committee - Photocopies, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Life After Ford Foundation (LAFF) Society - Miscellaneous, 1994-2009 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    LAFF Governance, Relations with Ford Foundation, LAFF Reunions, possible thematic shifts, other alumni groups
  - Letters on my Retirement, 1996 October (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Planning Phase Budget - Center on International Cooperation, New York University (2 folders), 1996-2016 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Comments on Proposal to Fund a Study of Multilateral Cooperation/Letters Regarding New Ford Foundation Funded Project at New York University (4 folders), 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 34-35, Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Letters Regarding Transition from Ford Foundation to NYU-Center on International Cooperation, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence from Last Months at the Ford Foundation (2 folders), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
    Correspondence relates to Forman's tenure as Director of the International Affairs Program, transition to NYU, and the subsequent work of the Ford Foundation in international affairs
- Monthly Calendars, 1980-1995; 3; 1.32 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes and 2 letter document boxes
  Calendars from Shepard Forman's tenure as Director of the Human Rights and Governance at the Ford Foundation, 1981-1991 and Director of International Affairs at the Ford Foundation, 1991-1996.
  - Monthly Calendar, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Monthly Calendar, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Monthly Calendar, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Loose Documents - Possibly from Calendars, 1981-1990 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Week-At-A-Glance Calendar, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Notepads - International Travel and Trip Notes, 1982-1996; 4; 2.08 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes and 2 legal document boxes
  Handwritten notebooks filled with trip reports and international travel notes from Shepard Forman's tenure as Director of the Human Rights and Governance at the Ford Foundation, 1981-1991 and Director of International Affairs at the Ford Foundation, 1991-1996. Most folders also include conference or trip agendas with names of individuals involved in meetings or presentations.
  - Southeast Asia, 1989 February 28-March 18 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    Meeting in Bangkok
  - Israel/Egypt, 1992 January 15-29 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    Africa/Middle East Program Review
  - Prague/The Hague, 1990 September (Box 6, Folder 58)
    Seminar: Parliaments and the Transition Toward Democracy
  - Moscow-Prague, 1993 July 18-31 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - The American Assembly, Arden House, 1992 April 23-26 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    The American Assembly, After the Soviet Union: Implications for US Foreign Policy, Arden House, Harriman Campus, Columbia University
  - India-China, 1992 March 1-13 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    New Delhi/Beijing
  - Cummington - International Affairs Retreat, 1992 October 8-9 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Moscow - Poland, 1992 July 15-24 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Arden House - Human Rights Consultation, 1992 June 26-28 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Warsaw, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Washington, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Loose Note - Yunnan/Kunming, undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI), 1991 November 13-15 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Prague - Social Welfare; Bratislava; Warsaw, 1991 April 15-24 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Moscow, 1994 October 18-26 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Kiev, 1994 October 13-17 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Lisbon, 1992 November 8-13 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Turin, 1996 May 13-17 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Moscow, 1995 September 11-16 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - China, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Istanbul, 1994 June 11-17 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    Varieties of Muslim Experience
  - Moscow, 1993 June 10-19 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    Center for Gender Studies
  - Moscow, 1993 April 18-25 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Moscow/Prague, 1994 September 27-October 2 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    Ukraine, Russia, Prague, Warsaw
  - Moscow - Pre-Board Meeting Notes, 1993 September 6-30 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - 1. Project Liberty; 2. Joe Nye; 3. Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS); 4. Atlantic Council, 1991 October (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - London, 1991 June 1-7 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Vienna/Warsaw, 1991 April 12-23 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    Conference: "The Future of Cultural Cooperation between the Countries of Western, Central and Eastern Europe: The Role of Foundations", European Cultural Foundation and the Institute for Human Sciences, in cooperation with the Council of Europe
  - Costa Rica, 1994 February 21-25 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Chile-Argentina, 1988 October 26-30 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    Southern Cone and American Council of Learned Societies Conference
  - India - Rural Poverty and Resources (RPR)/Governance Meetings - Bangalore, 1988 April 11-15 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    Asia-Plus Rural Poverty and Governance Staff Meeting
  - South Africa, 1982 April 20-29 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Zimbabwe, 1982 April 27-29 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    4/27 Johannesburgh - SA; 4/29 Salisbury - Zimbabwe; 4/30 Johnannesburgh - SA; 5/03 Rio de Janeiro - Brazil
  - Dakar, 1989 September 17-20 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    Africa Human Rights Meeting
  - Budapest, Hungary, 1990 January (Box 10, Folder 90)
    Vienna and Hungary
  - Cuernavaca, Mexico - Human Rights and Governance/Public Policy, 1990 January 28-February 4 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    Latin America and Caribbean Programs Regional Meeting: Programming in Human Rights and Governance in the 1990s
  - Asia Regional Meeting, 1992 March (Box 10, Folder 92)
    Beijing and New Delhi; The Club of Rome - International Conference on Evolving Concepts of International Cooperation for Development